good morning willem
so nice to see you again and thank you
for making time for this conversation
um i actually thought this morning it's
pretty much
to the day that we first met
um just down the road from here in a
little cafe um
two weeks after my daughter was born
three years ago
um so yeah it's interesting you were on
a holiday in mallorca
um so
this this series is a series of
conversations i'm having with people
that i
see in the larger field of what i call
the regeneration rising
um a global response to the converging
crises
um but also to the the potential that we
now have to say
we clearly know that exponential growth
on a finite planet is impossible and we
clearly see
the impact of the system that no longer
um will give
our children and children's children a
livable future on this planet
and we see that everywhere people are um
responding to this and then for me this
is this is a global movement that goes
beyond
um the practice of regenerative
development it's it's a whole
network of organizations some of them
have been around for 50 years some of
them have been set up in that last
five ten years that are now beginning to
um create a concerted
response and um so
what i normally invite people to do
my guests on the show is to start with
their personal story a little bit
to to tell how they got into
what they're doing um so i would love to
hear rather than me introducing you and
saying
well there's all these wonderful things
of you you've studied biology you
studied
tropical ecology agriculture and
environmental science
but it's always better to have the story
from the person
him or herself oh thank you very much
now it's uh thank you very much for
for joining um it's it's an honor to to
talk to you and to yeah
to to know you it's it's great to see
what you were doing and
and how that feeds very much into what
i'm doing and what
a lot of people are trying to establish
now
um yeah my personal story is
um starts when you wonder as a kid
uh some about something and that happens
with me as well
uh and i hope with a lot of other kids
it's still
uh you know we still have the
opportunity to
to to get these what i call magic
moments in their life
and for me it was when i was very young
already nature although i was raised in
amsterdam as an amsterdam city kid
nature was always around the corner and
for me all those small creepy animals
that you could find you know in
small bushes in the city um where were
small miracles and that's where it all
started i think
because i brought all those animals back
back home put them in kind of terraria
to observe them although my mom and dad
were you know sometimes
a bit looking what is he doing
uh and that was and i think that period
form
framed me uh and later on that brought
me to
you know to study biology and to to
understand
biodiversity and the diversity of
species and how
ecology is working and these kind of
things um
and i've yeah i've had experiences in
when when i was young as a kid
uh when these magical moments were very
powerful sometimes that you had the
feeling that
an animal is speaking to you or a tree
and and
maybe this sounds a bit weird but that's
that give you the feeling of
unity of whole wholeness and i think
that
wholeness feeling and experience never
i i kept it in a way i was able to to
maintain it
also when i grew up uh in the puberty
times and later on
which is really not easy because i'm i'm
like going through at the university of
amsterdam a degree in biology and then
studying
environmental science at the time um
i mean that must have been when did you
do
it it was in the 80s i finished my
studies in 87
1987. science was still pretty
reductionist like i mean when i did
biology at edinburgh in
the early 90s um i still remember some
of the professors calling ecology the
weird science
yeah not proper science yeah yeah and of
course
you know just so used right i studied of
course i studied ecology and tropical
ecology vegetation science uh enactus
focused on not on animals but
on flora fauna flores and vegetation
science
and yes that was of course ridiculous i
mean it was all
part of the the big you know
understanding and and and do
you know it was very much it's it it is
stella is i think a very much
scientific um beta uh science
uh which is good but yeah on the other
hand
i was able to go to nature and i was
able to stay in nature i
was doing these researches and and you
know all the things that were needed but
still i was able to be there
in the most wonderful places and because
i i you know as soon as i could could
could take a sabbatical within my study
period which i did
at that time it was still possible so i
took off a year
and went to india and sri lanka and you
know because i wanted to go to the
tropics so i bought
the the cheapest stickers i could find
at that time it was to colombo
and um yeah and the new world opened up
for me
and um and then i realized that you know
i need to go to
i need to work and understand tropical
ecosystems because they
were the most diverse i could ever see
and have found in my life
i know that in advance but i didn't you
know you need to experience it
and i think yeah i don't know i think i
was
able to to to do the scientific part
while maintaining the the miracle the
wonder part
and and and keep that because that was
the real driver within myself to
understand the scientific part
and and bringing those two together uh
because science did not always have an
answer or why a tree could speak to you
for instance
or whatever you know it's not speaking
it's more you know you could you could
feel uh it's about the feeling of of the
the yeah the healing power of nature
on the other hand while the scientific
background is super important as well
to understand how ecosystems work what
species do you interact with
all kinds of species how does the
colonization process
of reef works after uh you know a land
has been cleared
all these things are uh i was very
anxious now and still am
very anxious to understand how that
works so science is is a very much a
part of myself
ecological science agroscience because i
was very much interested in
in that world you know where aggro and
nature
was facing each other that was actually
the the
the basis of my studies um
and yeah the real old growth forest and
nature
the virgin places that could re-energize
people i find it fascinating
like i because it so resonates with my
story of
like i basically studied biology
and um worked on marine mammal ethology
behavioral science of marine mammals
and just got frustrated by um
seeing and sensing so much complexity
and then having to
keep it to what i could put into
statistically
significant boxes and add a p-value to
and anything else was anthropocentrism
anthropomorphism and whatever they would
would call it um projection and and
there was no way of including
this qualitative experience um
in the scientific discourse and so
that's why i initially left science and
then did a masters in holistic science
because when i saw that there was this
place at schumacher
college this new course that was
actually addressing all the things that
have
made me go away from science um it
i immediately signed up for it but it's
i think
it's it's a rare but well maybe not that
rare maybe there's a lot of
biologists and life scientists who have
to hold this
slight um well this is the schizophrenia
that in what some circles
where you where you talk hard science
you
you would get ostracized if you stop
talking about a tree
uh talking to you yeah oh but i never i
never talked about it
yeah i never talked about it you know it
was my world and
um but i observed it and i felt it and
you know
i think that i think you know when i was
young
um you know i i had the i don't know
what happened but at a certain moment i
i
i was told by by an animal that that
that actually when i i i i can really
explain
i remember that i was a kid i was very
young and
eight years old and was walking in in
france and i think it was in italy with
my mid with my father
and there were some italians standing
around a snake that they were trying to
kill
for me it was you know a wonder wow a
snake beautiful
and i was looking in the icing of that
snake and that snake
was still not dead it was laying there
you know it was you know just a grass
snake
you know not a very anonymous animal not
at all
and and i asked in myself
you know what are they doing to you and
immediately the answer of that snake
came back and they said they
are killing themselves
wow and at that moment it that was so
powerful
i really i certainly felt the unity in
myself you know
i'm the snake the snake is me those
italian people are the snake as well we
are all the same
but they don't know um because actually
they didn't know what they were doing
and if you
feel such a and i have some other
experiences in this this way later on as
well
and and and if you feel that and you can
nurture that
and keep it then you know science is
every is
an additional great opportunity to learn
more about
system about how we about you know about
all the scientific things of biology
and i was you know consuming that all
and trying to get more and more and
understand
reading all the books and getting more
understanding of all the plants and the
species and
i wanted to know all the animal species
of the world
and with their latin names and blah blah
all that stuff
because i because it didn't i did it
yeah it was kind of a separate part
while this other
secret or or unity feeling was there and
actually it was so powerful it could not
move it couldn't it wasn't possible to
get it away
and i was trying to go to places where i
could nurture both parts
the scientific parts with the species
and so on
and understanding landscapes reading
landscapes understanding how that was
working the interaction between organic
and
and organic material while also going to
those places where i could find
for instance indigenous people who could
tell me about that other world
and nurture me and in that part
and that was and and that those two
parts were
are part of myself and that's maybe why
i'm
in my career i'm incred yeah
increasingly being able to
build bridges between those two parts
also
whether it's with business or or or with
scientific science people because i can
speak their language
and with you know the the other world
that is
basically all the same
[Music]
but i i hope i can explain it you know i
do explain it uh
sufficient sufficiently you know that's
wonderful
i mean i hear a real kind of a
naturalist
speaking in the tradition of um humboldt
and heckle and goethe um who
were seeing the power of science but
also holding that larger holistic
perspective of how life is is one
planetary
interconnected process and and where
we're not spread from each other
um but yeah in your in your career you
then
um i wanted to actually get to this
bridge building that you just
named as well because that's what i've
observed when i look at what you've been
doing
um unfortunately somebody drilling out
there um
that you've really become a master in
weaving between
uh the the different sectors that
normally don't talk to each other and if
you've brought that
into your work with the i mean
the work with the iucn how did you move
from being a research
ecologist into um
conservation and even some some tourism
yeah yeah yeah so so you know when i
finished my studies as a tropical
ecologist at the end of the
80s beginning of the 90s it was of
course impossible to find a job
first of all no one was it was no
internet so you couldn't
apply for international jobs very easily
because they were you know you need to
look in all kinds of magazines
to find those jobs the second thing was
you know ecology was just not
and it was not a topic you know everyone
was working
to find a job in in the economic powers
world of making a business and and
public serving and so on
and tropical ecology for a dutch person
was even
more difficult so
[Music]
and as i was used to go out and wanted
to do expeditions and go to those
beautiful places in the world i found i
i teamed up with some other
biologists unemployed by biologists and
we decided to set up a company in
ecotourism
so that we could travel towards all
those places with our
knowledge and prepare that while others
were paying for it
because we brought some tourists with us
and that's
ended up in a quite successful company
it's probably the most successful dutch
company in ecotourism
in international ecotourism it's one of
the largest in europe i think
called snp na tourism and that company
still exists
and i was there for eight years almost
nine years and i developed the latin
america program
in you know many beautiful places like
venezuela colombia costa rica ecuador
peru these kind of places and was able
to organize expeditions right
small booklets and leaflets and and and
all every place so
for each destination we published a
booklet of like 100 pages on
on what on the natural phenomena we were
going to see
yeah and without internet so we needed
to look into and buy books
and you know so i went to bookstores in
colombia and peru and costa rica to find
those books shelves
all kind of books and trying to make
something out of it
at that time and um yeah so i learned i
think i learned two things there is
what business means how to earn your
money and how to develop programs
and manage them but also how to manage
people and groups and with them because
i was also their tour guide
so if you go with let's say 30 or 25
people into the jungle for
a month or three weeks that and you are
the leader
and you are 28 and they are like 30 40
or 50 or 60
then it is a challenge to to keep them
all together and keep them safe out and
get them safe out of that place again
it's a huge responsibility i had a
little
stint as a scuba diving instructor so i
know what you're talking about
like being being a group of people that
might be older
than you but you're fully responsible
for their them coming home safely
yeah yeah yeah and we had some difficult
times i mean uh one time
we lost we were in the jungle for the
whole night in costa rica and the
the police with helicopters were looking
for us because i i hired the wrong local
guide
the guy didn't know the way and another
time in colombia we just entered the
farc territory
that was in 1983 1993 and uh
yeah and we were kept uh in when we came
out of the territory the park wasn't
there but we were in that territory we
didn't know it actually
and when we came out of it we were i was
locked into uh you know in the police
station
and uh they did a hearing to uh
to explain what this group of dutch
people were doing in farc territory
so these kind of stories are are good
lessons learned
to to to help you to uh yeah you know to
understand what risks and
responsibilities are
i can i can sense i mean this is so
exciting what you've just shared up to
now that that
at some point you should write an
autobiography these kind of stories
sound really um i don't know
i'm not in the right habit yeah yeah and
then after that
how did you make the move into working
with the iocn then because
so at a certain moment i was fed up with
traveling because i was always traveling
and i couldn't
actually my dream was to work for
conservation organization and icin was
always on my
number one list because i loved the
principle i love the red list of
threatened species
understood how this huge network of
umbrella organization was working
so since i was a kid i already knew when
i was reading the magazines of wwf i
knew that
the organization behind wwf was iucn
that's where the science and the
knowledge was
so i wanted to to join iucn and
i decided to go back to the netherlands
and stay there for a while
became a teacher in biology just to have
a kind of
you know a job to stay there to look
into
magazines for positions potential
vacancies and at a certain moment there
was a vacancy
of iucn in the netherlands which
actually i didn't exist at irish and had
a presence any presence in the
netherlands
which was a very tiny organization the
irish national committee of the
netherlands and
they looked for a person who could
who could run a fund a small grants
facility for rainforest conservation
because they were able to get some
funding from overseas development in the
netherlands to fund rainforest
conservation projects this was in the
90s
1995 and i was able to get that position
and i ran that fund for four and a half
years almost five years
and made it successful was able to get
more funding on board from the dutch
government
and at a certain moment the board asked
me to become the director of ice
netherlands and then i said yes
but give me the time i need at least 10
years to get the potential of iocn
in the lens out and that's what i did
so from 2000 to 2012 i was able to
actually to fulfill that
dream and and i i remember signing it i
i remember when the board asked me i
said so this is the potential of irish
in the netherlands
and here are we now so give me 10 years
to fully
create this open up this potential with
funds with more members
with more influence with more
communication and dialogues also with
the business community
and yeah and that's what i did actually
this is this is what i
but i keep finding everywhere like
there's this close
group of people working within
regenerative development
with with certain they have a very very
um clear frameworks
and the word potential is is one of them
um but then there are lots of people who
naturally without necessarily
um knowing the the frameworks that
um uh kara sanford and and that
particular the regenesis group and that
lineage of regeneration has
developed are actually working naturally
from that from understanding nested
wholeness from understanding
the the the need for developmental
long-term evolutionary work
um and from starting from
starting from potential rather than
problems and oh yeah yeah
i find it really interesting because one
of the amazing things that
i think make the approach the full
returns approach of
common land which we'll get to in a
minute um so
unique is the
the conviction and the the audacity to
clearly say from the beginning this is
going to take 20 25 years
um and not pretend anything else and
and i didn't know that you you also when
when you took on the job with iucn
you told them don't give me just a few
years basically like
this is going to take some time and and
good transformation need to be curated
over time patiently um
yeah now yeah i i i don't know how this
happened but it's
it's exactly how you describe it it's i
always look from uh
you know first of all i love problems uh
i don't look them up
but they but i love problems because
then you have something to do
um and and yeah the the
uh the potential there's always a
potential and in nature there's always
your potential so i'm an optimist as
well
i'm not a although i could never do this
this work
because i've seen as you probably can
imagine and i'm sure you you recognize
that
yeah you see all the destruction and all
the negative stuff species loss
biodiversity loss you know all the the
degradation
degradation stuff and also and of course
all of those beats
that people live in those areas as well
but um
um sorry so like i was
just wanting to ask something about the
iucn work because in that time you
i mean basically iucn netherlands became
the strongest iucn
national um yeah yeah so so what what
happened was
um if you so if you want to use the
potential of a beautiful brand of icm
which is is you know you have signed
it's science-based and there are great
people working there i'm still a member
of that family
i will never leave that family because
i'm still associated with shin as a
fellow
in a commission but but
um if you see that potential of signs
of ngos you know more than a thousand
members working in the field of
the connection with the governments
because members there's all there are
also government members
and then the the you know the potential
that that you can have to
offer as a scientific based organization
with practical experience to to watch
the business
and get them on board on all kinds of
things
if you see that huge potential the
question is how can you
make sure that you can develop that
potential while
you're also part of a let's say a
bureaucratic organization
and um the the great advantage of a
national part of irish and was that i
was able know that that this this
national committee of icn within a
country
needs to is structured along the lines
along national lines
so i needed to convince my my my friends
at the ngos who were a member in the
netherlands 37 organization i think at
that time when i started like 28 when i
left like 37
and they were my board they were
so so if i could convince them to open
up that space
without competing with them because
there were large you know wwf
netherlands is a large and important
organization so you don't need
you don't want to compete you want to
add value to
all of them and i was looking for that
space
how can i as ice and netherlands add
value to those
37 organizations add value to the dutch
government
with their funding mechanisms and
overseas development aid
and add value to the icn national
international network
including the scientists and the
secretariat in switzerland
without competing but but still how can
i open up that space
and that was i think my biggest
challenge to open up that space make
sure that i was able to raise my
own funds our own funds without asking
funds from the swiss headquarters
but able would be able to add more
members internationally through
you know as through our grand mechanism
we could ask new
foundations in whatever countries to
also
to become an asian member so actually
this
ended up after 10 years in more almost
extra new members local ngos for eisen
international
and and um when people but but it is
it's a balancing act because you you
know you need to talk a lot and
so that people get an understanding yet
we're not competing we are adding value
to the network and the union
and that was my most yeah that was the
thing i was always worried about and
tried to
to do that again if i find that that's
also a pattern that i i
see um
through observing your way of working
also in with common land that it's all
about
acknowledging that there can be
tendencies
for different organizations as they come
together to do work to
together actually to start competing for
funding sources and for
competing for turf in what they
traditionally are doing and that
the trick is bringing everybody with a
vision that is long-term enough and big
enough and holistic enough
into a space where they understand that
they can shift from competitive
advantage to collaborative advantage and
they can
actually stay in doing what they're
doing well
and that's great because then the others
don't need to do that but they can trust
that that's
somebody yeah but they can build
something bigger
and more transformative together which
is the the collaborative advantage yeah
i think you hear you
hear you um and i i didn't realize that
at that time when i was doing it but
basically what you say yeah we were
creating a kind of a space
and within that space there was there
was space for organizations
to to work with to work raise funds
together
to do lobbying together based on the
different roles and
and networks the different organizations
that people have
and um i think that's why i see
netherlands could grow
extensively because we could be we're
building both
the trust towards the dutch government
as well as
the international headquarters as as
we were bringing new energy to members
and bringing in new members as well
and you also i mean you you made very
good inroads with philanthropic money
around the world and were able to
through through ioc and funnel
a lot of funds into projects all over
the world he financed many projects in
in south america and and another place
in
central america um yeah i mean but maybe
maybe two to
to to bring the expectations a little
bit down it was small grants so
it was not a lot of money and i think
the overall budget was like 10 million
euros per year
so it it was not the hundreds and
hundreds millions um
but but what i realized is that the
small grants
are those seed money in institute for
grassroots organizations are essential
and if you can help them to move then
towards larger grants
uh from other institutions um you know i
think that's that was what our role at
that time and
is and and still is i think the
direction
this is this is also fascinating i
wasn't going to go there but you know
you made me think about when when i was
working with the team that had set up
the lush spring price um
the lush setup a few years ago and
and we were like they invited a team of
judges to help them select who gets the
prize
and they're relatively small prizes
they're um
basically kind of in the range of
from 10 to 25 000 so minuscule to some
extent
compared to the big funding
organizations
but we realized very quickly that there
was such wealth
in all the organizations that had made
it into the runner-up stage had been
selected and bettered by the
pre-selection process and then
12 international judges and all the
judges were constantly saying
we're looking 52 projects and really 49
or 48 of them should be funded
um but we can only give 11 prizes
and so so we started to explore could we
not
network with other prizes around the
world and create a platform where all
these runner-ups are showcased
as wonderful projects that deserve um
funding and that have already been
vetted by a
selection process and out of that group
this platform that is still
somewhat in development currently
looking for the next stage of funding
called
the re-generosity um
um and one of the central things that
you just made me think about is
precisely this problem that there are
lots of foundations out there
for whom 500 000 is a small ground
that on the board of directors meeting
doesn't even
get discussed just somebody says and
then there's these five
projects that we also want to fund and
they either just
sort of say okay or they they say no but
let's put that money somewhere else
and but for many projects that are doing
very place source place based grassroots
community
sourced regeneration
getting 500 000 in one bulk might
already be
a bit too much to handle what they would
need
is 50 000 every year for 10 years to get
ready then maybe receive 500 000.
here you point out a critical element
and that's what we
that's what i took over in common land
and that's you know
if you want to bring change in the
landscape and quite often ngos want to
do
that because they see nasty situations
deforestations
whatever they want to bring change and
that's it the charity world is focused
around results
and uh short-termism funding
which is it has its history you could
say or
until many of those vendors need to need
to
need to reply to their vendors where the
where the money will go
and whether the results are are achieved
but in difficult circumstances where all
those local ngos and indigenous
communities are working
you can't predict you can't predict
exactly
how your money is spent and what kind of
results
uh it will will will be achieved
so what you need to do actually is try
is try is
to find the staff
so get the best people there local
people
make sure that they don't need to worry
about their salary
so that they can do their work well for
the long term
long run and what is the long run yeah
of course
our work is about decades
it is difficult but but it's you know
plants or trees do do grow but you don't
grow faster because
because you put some pour some money
over it and and planting trees is
i always say planting trees is the most
easy thing to do with getting the trees
mature
over let's say 100 years that is the
most difficult things to do i mean
google and amazon can't do that
you know all those tech companies they
can't even do that we need to have good
people
in the field make sure that those trees
are not good
uh just as an example
so so um funding
of projects mean for filling of projects
it means that you need to make sure that
that
the staff is well covered and that you
have
reliable trustful knowledgeable people
and human people human beings who can
who can where you can take away a little
bit of the worries of
that they need to think about
fundraising every
six months because thinking about friend
racing that
sucks so much energy basically that you
can't do your work
and you are hired to do the work on the
ground with farmers with local
conservationists with indigenous people
with
all those people living there to to
protect restore
and bring people together to transform
their vision and life into a
regenerative way of living and that is
very difficult
so um that's why it's one of the reasons
why
when i started commonland was that i
wanted to focus on
first build a strong organization with a
good staff
that don't need to worry every every
month about print raising
and then we can create a vehicle to work
with others
and and help them to to make sure that
they can
do whatever is needed at the landscape
yeah
i understand that at some point despite
of all your love and all all your
amazing service um
to iucn it was the sea
that you grew out of in the iuc and the
international union for the conservation
of nature i
i sense that you you you step beyond
conservation to regenerate
and the answer is it's now it
i'm still a conservationist and a very
and so so
it's not that i stepped out of
conservation i mean i i
i'm still connected to i assume for
other organizations that work on
conservation and
we just celebrate at the moment uh the
publication will be released next month
on
20 years of uh land acquisition funds
which i started in 2001 with lottery
money
at iucn so that is buying lands to
conserve it
locally with local or ngos of course and
and that
you know we i think we spent more or
less 10 million
over the last 20 years in tiny protected
areas
that we could that we needed to buy
because that was the only way to protect
it
you know if you have some small endemic
species that live there
within a small water catchment or
rainforest area and you
the only way is to to to make sure you
protect those species by buying that
land
otherwise a mining company or an oil
pump company will consume it
it's a very powerful tool um
so i'm very happy that that this fund
still continues
what i was getting with with the
conservation is that
even if you have a reserve like that it
doesn't necessarily fully protect it
no no so exactly so i'm going to that
point exactly so so what my frustration
now
yeah but what i realized after so many
years working 17 years working with iucn
in the netherlands especially abroad
internationally
and funding a lot of projects that you
could indeed fund
let's say a thousand hectares projects
of rain
converting rain forest in let's say the
brazilian amazon
but then at a certain moment
that island of rainforests
it became an island of rainforest in a
soy belt
or in a palm oil belt because around it
everything was cleared for monocultural
agricultural cropping or livestock or
whatever
and for me it was important to bring
those things
together you know i'm not against
agriculture but i see
the danger of large monoculture
agricultural deserts
and and we need to weave these things
into a landscape approach and
within irish and we always call that a
mosaic landscape
and the concept of mozi landscape was
built upon
what within our i should be called the
ecosystem approach
and the ecosystem approach is a
wonderful document if you can find it on
the web you should google it
because it it was actually
[Music]
written by people from isian in the 90s
and it was accepted by the conventional
biological diversity in 1995
but it was a theoretical concept
and for me i always thought you know
that ecosystem report means people need
to live
within an ecosystem approach and
we have the scientific parameters of
what an ecosystem approach is
but now we need to make it practical but
how
because otherwise you you know it
doesn't work it stays within
international conventions
and and scientists can use it but you
know we need to live it actually
and when i had built that all that
experience
all those experiences within iucn with
grants and working with business and so
on and
ngos at a certain time in 2010
and nine i realized i need i need to
need to go towards the next step for
myself and i probably cannot do this
next step within an institution like
iecn
but i didn't know that at that time for
me the moment
the the moment when i when my eyes were
opened was when i met john d liu
in 2009 at a conference in tahlberg in
sweden
and he gave a presentation and um he
showed his
beautiful footage of the lust plateau
and then and i immediately saw that the
list plateau actually
was implementing in a kind of a way the
ecosystem approach
and i thought wow now i've got finally
someone who
filmed and documented large-scale
an ecosystem approach so i went to him i
said listen guy
i don't know you you don't know me i'm
bill i'm from the netherlands i'm
heading out in the lance you're a john d
view
but we need to work together and this
again
without knowing it i said and we need to
work together for the rest of our life
all else is history yeah well i didn't
know the guy he didn't know me
and then we said together we were
talking almost for three days and
the whole conference we forgot about the
conference and we were talking the whole
con you know talking for three days at
night because it didn't you know it was
in summertime in sweden
almost no night and um and that went to
a corporation
a collaboration so i hired john he came
working for us at that time with iucn
he was able to produce with my support
to our support
uh documentaries that were
everywhere like green gold and like
like a time of change in climate
uh bbc documentaries and so on so we
were teaming up together
uh because he could speak out and he
could communicate
that's this very well in his way of of
communication
and meanwhile it gave me the time to
rethink
and also conclude at a certain moment
that i needed to leave aisha and
need to take more time a sabbatical
which i did in 2012
to interview farmers and investors
because if we want to change this system
and build
the ecosystem approach into a economic
landscape approach um we need to bring
onboard
all those external parties business
investors
but you know always living there
indigenous people
and farmers they are living on the rural
countryside
and of course some other people but they
are
they are impacting that landscape in a
positive or a negative way
if it is in a negative way we consumers
through corporates and investors are
behind that because we want all kinds of
things out of those landscapes
um so i went to those i took a year off
i actually asked i quit with my job and
the next i remember the day you know
first you have a whole office business
secretaries and a pa and whatever and
then the next day you're sitting alone
like here in my room
and i say okay um and my mailbox was
greatly going down
okay where am i what did i do had no
income had a kid and a family so it was
a bit scary
and risky but on the other hand it also
felt very much free
and i'm a little bit entrepreneurial you
know it felt like you know
now i can take the next step of course
this danger of you know no
income was becoming readily bigger and
bigger but they were
finally after a few months people came
to me and said how can i help you and
arrest some people with some
deeper pockets than i had and they
helped me to survive
which was wonderful so
i was able to visit and travel a lot in
that period
and i asked farmers and investors
basically two questions so i went to
london new york
frankfurt and amsterdam and spoke to
investors especially institutional
investors of pension funds
and i went to poor farmers and wealthy
farmers
in in the us in the uk
in europe france the netherlands
spain but also places like india ghana
south africa colombia ecuador so
several places turkey and i spoke
i met all those farmers and asked and
investors and basically asking two
questions
um the first question question was what
is your biggest frustration
and the second question is was what is
your dream
and almost all the farmers whether they
were poor or rich
it didn't matter uh answered on the
frustration
that the biggest frustration was that
they could not hand over their land in a
better condition
as they have received it and
when i asked about their dreams their
dreams were where
in general that dreams where we want to
live
and produce in a landscape that
is alive that is green
uh where people can live and come back
we don't we the biggest you know their
dream was we want to have
that the people come back because they
were living in abandoned lands
quite often people were moving to cities
which is still
the big trend as you know and they
missed their you know communities
in spain schools were closed churches
were closed you know the
swimming pool was closed so and only all
people were living there
so the community was number one and
then the next though in their dream is
was
give us a community back and then give
us a landscape back where we can produce
within an ecological setting so that we
don't harm the landscape
and we know how to do that but we are
not you know we're not
uh financed to do that we're finding two
other things
that was the farmer story that the
investment the investor story
uh you know i just summarized it was
interesting as well
so i spoke to people from our age and
then they some of them were all that had
kids you know and puberty
kids in their puberty and and then our
twenties or thirties
and when i asked the question about
frustration says that they said in
general
we are i'm frustrated because i'm
investing
in destroying the future of my kids and
my kids are telling me that
and blaming me for it but you know i've
got a big house two cars you know i
can't step out of this job
so it's so they were actually they had a
crisis within
a generational crisis um and that was in
even before greater turnberg until i
came on
we're pointing this out and when you
when i was asking them about their dream
um it was more about yeah
their dream would be in their job first
of all it would be that they could
invest
in the future of their kids but that
means that their dream would be
that they could find pipeline of real
positive
sustainable projects but they couldn't
find them
the projects that they were funded ever
cold sustainable
where projects that were doing less harm
[Music]
and and that was their so lack of
pipeline on the one side
and lack of funding to do good on the
other side at farmland level
those two things were connected of
course and i thought how can i
build that bridge in a language that
both farmers
ecologists as well as investors and
business will understand
and that brought me back to simplify the
whole discussion on ecological
degradation
simplify to one sentence and that
sentence is
maximization of return on investment per
hectare
leads to degradation
because you know in every business
school and you know
when i was in my sabbatical i became a
fellow at the rotterdam school of
management as well
at business school they didn't know you
know at all what ecology was
so but every business school still is
teaching
maximization of return on investment is
the big holy grail that's where you
you know your destination lies as a
business person
but if you put at two words per
hectare you get biodiversity loss
soil erosion production loss loss of
resilience at landscape level
water scarcity all these things we don't
want to know deforestation pollution
you get it all and so i simplified
that maximization of return on
investment per hectare is the common
belief economic system that is
suffering you know that's creating all
these nasty things at the landscape
level the interesting thing is i
realized in my discussions with the
investors and with the farmers
that the word return was critical
everyone is looking for a return
but what is a return when investors
speak about return they only mean
financial returns and they prefer to
speak in double digits
when the farmer speaks about return the
first return he wanted was people
let the people come back the second one
was
yes i would love to have some more
income of course
but sustainable income but i don't want
to get rid of my land because that's
holy that's my you know i
that's my whole history it's my land
and and generations before that so for
farmer land is super important which of
course
and especially for indigenous people
it's even much more important because
they have a longer history
and of course there's tension with
colonists and so on but i won't go into
that now
so return was critical the word return
[Music]
so i decided you know if if that
maximization of financial return per
hectare
is the real stuff simplified in one
sentence
then there are losses at the landscape
level but if you look into how many
losses there are there are so many
losses
and i brought it down to four losses
because
people who are living there lost their
sense of meaning and their pride
that's what i noticed when i spoke to
farmers and i knew it
already for for for decades when i spoke
to indigenous people
the second loss is that they lost their
community and they lost
because jobs were going away so they
lost jobs social capital
and the third loss was biodiversity
you know the whole vegetation cover all
that had to do with biodiversity
and species and the natural system and
as a result of that the fourth loss at
the london is
financial capital because at a certain
moment
the system is so degraded that people
move away
that you can't do anything with those
wastelands anymore
no financial capital so those four
losses
are the basis of my you could say model
that i designed
to create a language model to build a
bridge between all those different
groups
and that was if we want to restore
landscapes
based on an ecosystem approach the
science underneath
then we need to talk about four returns
we need to return inspiration we need to
return
social capital jobs we need to return
biodiversity
and that will give sustainable return
of financial capital or you could say no
return of sustainable financial capital
so that was the first layer of the model
and that but still theory because if you
explain it like you and you can put
indicators under those
different returns return of inspiration
is probably the most difficult
but the most important one and you could
you can
you can put a lot of indicators under
that and that's what i did and i wrote
it now
but to get it landed at the landscape
level you need to talk about landscape
zoning
and that is where ecologists like you
and me where you know understand
how zoning works and you need to think
first of all you need to understand what
an ecosystem is
so i was always approaching landscape
from an ecosystem perspective it means
that you really
yeah you're talking about thousands or
hundred thousands of hectares
because this is about a large landscape
if you talk about uh
the ecosystem of the amazon there are
different
type of rainforests in the amazon basin
and you can see the amazon is a huge
area but if you look into it carefully
you can say okay there's a different
there's a type of
amazon forest between two river
catchments there
or tributaries of the amazon and if you
take that area it's maybe fifty thousand
or a hundred thousand or even
five hundred thousand hectares and
within
these areas actually in a landscape
perspective you need to bring it back to
three zones
normally we bring it back to two zones
that's what
happens all over the world you have an
economic zone where people
are active land use mining agriculture
infrastructure cities buildings etc
and you have what we call a protected
area
that is where we say okay their nature
should be more dominant in that place
and so we have a natural zone protected
area
or even still quite not protected but
it's still natural
but it may move into an economic zone
and you have an economics
town but the in-between zone is actually
where the magic
can happen of course we need to protect
as much as possible
especially now in these days and yes
we understand the economic zone but the
in-between zone is almost
not present in most countries and we
call that we call that the combined zone
so that's the place where you can
produce two things
you produce food and fibers
with agriculture and you produce
biodiversity
and if you do that well then you create
regenerative
agricultural or regenerative
agroforestry systems
and we know that that this is possible
from you know a lot of experience and
nowadays in the regenerative agriculture
and permaculture we know that this is
possible
but it means we need to have a change
it's a mindset change but it's it's so
fascinating how important mimetics and
framing
actually are in all of this because the
classic
um ecologist language would call that a
buffer zone
a buffer is is is a framing that makes
it common there's this and there's this
and we have something to keep them apart
yeah it's um but the combined zone
is is the opposite it's it's again
bridge building it's saying okay
we there is a way that we can um
increase bioproductivity and diversity
in this area
and still do it in a way that we
regeneratively harvest we
improve the landscape but we actually
get value out of it
and because we do that we create enough
financial return to the people in the
in the industrial zone in the in the um
sorry but
the the economic zone but the economic
zone that
that there is no reason to invade
the protected zone in in a way that
um happens all over the world where you
get
large nature reserves biodiversity
reserves with
un labels on them and they're not worth
the paper that they're written on
because
um people have economic pressures and
and therefore
the reserve can't be enforced but if you
have
a combined zone that helps you to
enforce the reserve
now that that's that's that is very much
true and i realized something else
that is the combined zone is
um the combination is also
get now farmers get a better
understanding of what the natural zone
can provide for
can mean for them through the combined
zone because they're going to rethink
what this combination of biodiversity
and productivity means
and for city people um of course they
know quite often
how important the natural zone is but
they have no idea what it is to be a
farmer
and and they can build a bridge to the
or to the conservationist or the
indigenous uh community
so so um but you need to have a kind of
a landscape
and an ecosystem that covers that so
it's important that that
that you understand what a natural
ecosystem
is and where this mosaic landscape
setting or
three-zone setting uh can be
part of and that's why we when we
so so this is so so the four turns
is about measurements and uh the
opposite of the maximization of the
return on investment
idea the the three zones is how to
deliver the four returns within a
landscape
and the last component is of course time
uh being so much frustrated about
projects
of four years or three years of maximum
five years with
donors and so on i very much looked into
the large infrastructure
world you know if you want to plan a
high-speed train between
madrid and paris you can't do that in an
overnight
maybe in china they do it in a few years
but in europe it will take more years
and
in other places it will take a lot of
years so
um time is super important and here of
course
the ecologists would say we need a
decade we need
a century but the investor
who has been used working with large
infrastructural investments
dredging or building cities or whatever
will probably say no we need a decade
or two so i i brought in
two decades minimum so 20 years uh also
because that is
very much in tune with generational
thinking
so a generation and so i said okay
four returns are delivered by a three
zone approach in
minimum 20 years uh because then you
first of all you you can build trust
within a landscape
in 20 years you can't build trust with
consultants and ngos if you have only a
four years project
you can build relations that's right the
building trust is very difficult
and it can go away before you know it
and and because these things are going
like that people come
and go in a landscape and um
yeah that's that's how it all started so
what i did is i wrote it down
published it and asked my my colleagues
from the ecological world from unep from
wwf from iucn
to to reflect on this document and
and that happened in 2000 between 2013
and 14 and in 2015 the second document
was published with all those
people having looked at it at the
erasmus university the rocksman school
management and
within the iucn commission on ecosystem
management so that is the
the ecology the science scientists of
ecologists within iucn
so i bought i brought those two worlds
together in one publication the business
school
world and the ecology scientists so
yeah that well it was not easy but it
was
very fascinating to do i mean a link in
when i
post this um conversation i will link
the the two documents
because it's it's this exists
downloadable as a pdf
in spanish and in english um
yeah yeah and it's maybe it's yeah it's
maybe a bit technical but uh
yeah for me it was it was important to
write that down
and then then when when is the actual
founding of
common land as an organization
so i so it took me so more or less a
year
after i left iucn i published my first
paper
which was not yet ready in november
2012.
uh i think it's somewhere on the web
still and um
and then i found it commonly in april
2013 because then
i remember at a certain moment you had
this you had this this feeling
yes i got it i've got it and i wrote it
down you know but but very superficial
in in
pdfs and whatever in and it was not yet
publicable
but i was so anxious to immediately do
it
that i thought yeah what can i do can i
join wwf or iocn some some of them
of my former colleagues asked me in
switzerland can you join us
i thought you know maybe i need the
space first to test it
and the only way to test it you need to
have a team and yeah you need to have
the freedom to test it so you need to
have the resources and
let's say the legal constituency to do
it in a in a way you want you want to do
it
and that's when i thought let's let's
let's find the common lens
in 2013 in april we founded it
first in a different name ecosystem
restoration
foundation or ecosystem return
foundation but then we asked others to
look at it and they said yeah this is
such a difficult name no one will get it
you need to think about others as well
and
uh it turned in in mar i think in april
no in july 2014 we termed
we changed the name in common land yeah
and
but it's grown so rapidly now you have
what 30 some staff and you you have
four major pilot projects in in
south africa in australia in the
netherlands and in spain
and a growing network of partnerships
all around the world um to
to take this approach to all countries
yeah luckily enough and that was only
possible because i found a co-founder
and that was that was a philanthro that
was actually a businessman
in the netherlands um and i remember
that
i didn't know him but he at a certain
moment he called me after my first
publication and he said listen you are
doing interesting work
let's talk and we had a very
yeah we were talking to each other let's
say within a year also through his
the his the director of his
philanthropic foundation
at that moment and um yeah he didn't
he didn't he got it but uh he wanted to
know me better and so on but at a
certain moment we decided
we will we will create common land
together because he had the resources
the financial resources
and i had the knowledge network and the
idea
and and and that's how we did it
together so actually you could say
uh we co-founded uh common land together
of course i started i founded it in 2013
and he
joined um he said yes to finned
the first process in december 2013 so
from 2014 onwards
is is this the gentleman behind because
i just recently um i
had a conversation with somebody who
kept talking to me about common earth
and then i common dot earth and
and which is the organization that grew
out of the conversation i've had with
um cloud burst foundation and the
commonwealth secretariat and was
was officially launched last october and
the website is common with two m's
dot earth and then i found out that
there's a website
called the big c big o small m
[Music]
exactly so and so what happens yeah
exactly so what happened is that at that
time
um uh mr palm that's his name
that's the big business man here in the
netherlands uh uh weiner
where you know where we found each other
you could say
uh he come from this whole family
business network and i came from the
ecological
network and yeah he started this
command foundation it means come on
and um which which indeed turns
into this command.earth website
and uh so that is our that started to
become our major offender
and when i started comment i he was you
know
i could we could finally team up and
said listen what i need
is long-term funding for a team if i
want to accelerate
this whole difficult transformational
process at a landscape scale
and make sure that we can go fast i
don't want to worry every four
or three or two years about raising
funds for a team and i need
25 people so and and that's basically
the minimum multi-disciplinary team to
kick-start this whole work
i've set up before as i said i've been
working in the in the startup phases of
smp naturalizing and ioc and so i knew
what it was to
create startups and move from startup to
a scalar
and of course if you move to a scale if
you need different kind of people
people who are more structured and we
are in that phase now so that's
wonderful
but but in that phase i needed to build
a team
and i knew what time what type of people
i needed you know
people in the space of creating
co-creation processes
i needed people with financial expertise
with ecological expertise
um business expertise business
development expertise
so all that's how to bring them all
together and work together
at a landscape skill and then work and
identify landscape so i
i knew of course due to my background i
knew
what kind of criteria you were you need
to look at before starting a project at
the land
you know within a concrete landscape and
decided to first start in countries that
were less
difficult you know spain is less
difficult than
southern sudan but southern sudan needs
a lot of ecological
restoration projects of course but if
you start there you know you probably it
will be more tough
and this is already is not easy so i
started to work in countries like
australia
south africa spain and later on also in
the netherlands
could you explain a little bit um also
for my benefit of how
how to maybe um
ground the similar process maybe in
collaboration
with with you and and common land here
on majorca
the the actual process of engagement
because the largest of those
um core pilot projects that the common
land has is the one in spain the alvara
it's a million million
hectares yeah um a huge area in
most here um how do you i mean i know a
little bit you use a pro
um process u of theory eu approach to
create um a multi-stakeholder
process of yeah now there are basically
yeah there are some steps you need to
take into consider look at
first of all there's so many places over
the world that are degraded you know
we are talking about two billion
hectares you know double the size of
china that is degraded and it's probably
too
much more and it's going fast so there
are lots of opportunities
everywhere you can do this everywhere um
i've realized by the way now after seven
years of testing and building the
concept
that the four returns three zone
approach works everywhere
uh to my actually to my surprise also in
marine areas
it's it's uh it's an ecosystem approach
it's a
practical translation of the of the of
this beautiful ecosystem approach
this is precisely where i want to go
about my yoga because
the lyrics have the marine terrestri
so exactly so so for instance we also
work together with the charles darwin
foundation and the gala on the galapagos
which is a similar way of you know like
if you talk about an island situation
but so some steps
um if in some criteria so yes
uh it's easier to work in in better
covenants countries than in
weak countries less stable countries but
but it can it can be done everywhere um
i think the business drivers need to be
clear so what kind of agriculture or or
land use activities are there and are
there potential to transform that from
the destructive agriculture to more
regenerative and positive agriculture
that's important and if there's already
a potential like the almonds in spain
you know it's easy to not not easy but
it is still easier to transform an
almond monoculture into an agroforestry
system
than than something that's just not
there or cereals into
so the the very important also is are
there people who live there
want to stay there and really are open
for change and have the leadership guts
and
skills to do that we very much carefully
look to
this that could be an ngo it could be
you know but but
people's kind of breeding ground of
people that
understand this and are open for change
what i also realize is that crisis is
important the the more severe the crisis
is at the landscape scale the easier
people are want to transform
and change um and of course the
ecological conditions
you know um we can talk at length
by the altitude in spain but you know
from an ecological perspective it is
pretty difficult because
the trees are not going growing fast you
have a
you have a cold winter and a hot summer
so the growing seasons are actually only
in spring
and in autumn while for instance in the
tropical wet system
you have a almost a growing season all
year round
and you see the difference much faster
and then within a few years you can you
know
a secondary forest in a rainforest area
if you have the right conditions
within a within two years you have you
have meters of vegetation
so and that's definitely not the case in
spain
so so all these things you need to take
into consideration and then you have of
course the policies
that are available and the potential
offenders that might be interested
in these places so you need to look into
all these different layers before you
take the right
the decision to work there but number
one are the people
you know if you have a core group of
good people who really want
to work on this for decades
then then you have you have something
very
very very powerful three years ago when
when when we
met on your holiday here in mallorca and
we already
sort of started a conversation about the
potential
in both majorca and the balearic islands
with
with this a lot of international global
attention
a lot of people know these islands come
here regularly on holiday or even have
second homes here
um it's a unique opportunity
to look at the combination between how
does terrestrial
regeneration and restoration um
connect with the marine restoration
that needs to happen and how are they
actually because
traditionally you get the blue
conservationists and the green
conservationists and
they don't really um look at how they
work together
and then we already spoke about the the
dramontana and some of the
landowners that that could potentially
be interested and
things have moved on a lot and there's
definitely all the conditions you've
just named
like um the big industry that wasn't
listening three years ago is tourism
because they were still making
huge amounts of money but then you said
you need a crisis
both at an economic and a landscape
level and we've
tourism pushed the crisis at the
landscape level in terms of rapid
degeneration of the island
and the the sea and now kovit has pushed
another enormous economic um crisis
where both political and business
players probably while they have less
money
to support a transition at the moment
because they're
in panic of um they have certainly a lot
more willingness to
talk about a transformation and then
then there's all sorts of
particularly in the marine area there
are lots of organizations that have
already set up and doing wonderful work
and
it actually needs what common land
and you yourself are so skilled in that
they're bringing them together
and and doing this um when we were
talking about that uh
and you know the grating of an island in
this case majorca is that
i easily identify the zoning
so so with the zoning the storytelling
also starts
so so this is first of all you need to
how to bring together all those
different opinions and people
uh you know one lives in a mountain the
other one in the city or whatever
uh you need to to tell you need to bring
them together at the landscape level and
tell them and
and create that story together and what
what our experiences
is that these four turns three zones and
20 years helps
there is a very powerful tool to help to
understand
give them a sense of place where am i
what am i doing here
how is that connected to that
mountaintop over there
that that's a very powerful tool and the
second thing is because these
you start with inspiration and start
again to question
what do you what is your frustration and
what is your dream and if you ask that
question to those different people in
bring them together in a circle
and we use the the the theory you model
developed by the presenting institute
you know you create a
real powerful understanding of
of them together but also what it means
for them to live in that specific
landscape and how these landscapes are
interconnected
and if you can bring that to the next
level of
creating a story of in this case of
majorca
where you say okay in mallorca we have
these three zones
and we we have uh
the potential of the combined zone which
is not yet very much developed
and we had the potential of the natural
zone that could be more protected and
more
nurtured or whatever and we have the
potential of the economic zone
that was first of all driven by tourism
but without tourism we need to look into
other opportunities
you know what does that mean and then
you start to create
um to build in uh let's say community
feeling
business thinking but underneath
before you know what you start to talk
about all about ecology
and about what is the ecological
foundation to make this happen and and
you will realize that of course
agriculture or the marine area are
interconnected
you don't want to have the polluted
water and erosion stuff into the water
and all that stuff
so it is a it's just a powerful tool and
and without knowing it sometimes it
sometimes really goes fast like in spain
people start to think about but if this
is the case
then my business actually should turn
into another type of
business or maybe tweak it a little bit
you know use less pesticides
uh don't clove or till too much all
these things are gradually happening
because people start to talk about it
and then
yeah within a few years and that's what
we've seen in all those places where we
work
farmers are going to stock with each
other and ask
others for advice how they do things so
a conventional farmer is going to start
to start to talk with the organic farm
and say hey
i thought you were crazy but maybe uh
you are doing things that are
interesting for me to know and you know
that conventional farmer don't need to
be turned immediately into an organic
farmer
but he can already deal with some things
or and that's what we see everywhere
so we are not promoting organic farming
but we promote
an understanding of what ecology means
and if you
start to farm with nature what will that
mean for your business
but also for yourself there's another
another box opens and uh i've seen it
talking with farmers in australia or in
spain with us and south africa you know
the
the meaningfulness comes back people
farmers immediately actually they
understand what is good
or bad for their soil and if they are
forced into
you know because of we consumers buy
cheap things
or agro tech companies sell them
whatever
they're at their recipes if they're
forced into a kind of
way of dealing things then they tend
to forget what it is to be reconnected
to
soil life or um or
a beautiful landscape or a cow under
the shade of a tree instead of uh
other times you know so so it is it is
um
it really taps into the soul of people
and and that's where the i call it the
soil soul connection comes from
uh we all come from the soil of course
yeah i mean
if you understand how evolution works
but but
um it's good to be to find that
connection again
and that is a powerful driver i remember
talking to an australian farmer
i think it was last year it was a family
a wife
and a man and they changed from
conventional farming
through organic farming on their way to
regenerative farming
and of course they went through a whole
lot of steps
and i i don't know whether they were
certified or not but
i i remember that the farmer said yeah
you know it's so difficult to understand
how all these ecological stuff works but
every time i'm i'm just discovering new
things
and that makes me happy and i'm asking
go out to other farmers and speak online
and whatever to
learn how it works but it never stops
and then his wife said yeah it i see him
so make it makes me happy to see him
happy
with all these new developments and we
feel that it's cleaner and we have
almost less chemical stuff but i also
need to say some
something that i don't like of organic
farming and regenerative farming
and and that is we cannot plan our
holidays again
because the recipe farming is gone but
the nice thing of recipe farming is you
know
we knew the whole we knew in advance for
a whole year
how the year would look like and now uh
we just don't know whether we can go for
a holiday because
maybe this organic stuff will develop in
something that we don't know and
and that's for me as a wife it was
difficult so it's
it's nice how these things immediately
have an impact on lives of people but in
general it is positive
and now i think the markets and we as
consumers need to make sure that this
and all i also hope with the carbon
prices that this will be driven into a
new way of
living that will enable us to create
and and restore landscapes
and bring ecology back in our mindset as
well
from you i mean because
comet land has grown rapidly and more
and more partners are coming
online in in large um
landscape projects in the global south
and so on
um i'm sometimes wondering is mallorca
and just a few small balearic islands
with their
um relatively small surface area
um still an interesting project to
commonland
to engage with i mean for for me what i
see so
such a huge potential here is that it is
this close connection between land and
sea
and the the project of with the local
university
and also investigating um
the climate change dimension of
the four main mediterranean climate
zones
um very dry slightly more humid that
there's roughly four
groins on the mediterranean and we have
them all on the island because of the
mountains and the diversity of
mallorca and so there's a lot of
transferable
knowledge that and also it being islands
what i've realized living on this island
now for 10 years is that
there's a an identity that is cross
nationalities that that unites the
mediterranean basin
across the islands because for thousands
of years the people on the island
are they might the islands belong to a
nation
but the people on the islands are the
seafarers
the the are the sons and daughters or
grandchildren of of people who have done
the interchange between all those
nations along the mediterranean so
so a new york genetically has just as
much relationship to
somebody on sardinia on corsica or
actually more
than to somebody in madrid um and and
so so there's this potential that if we
create
an example of long-term landscape
regeneration combining marine
and terrestrial um on the balearics
that that could travel along the
mediterranean basin and then of course
if if there's a lot of research in in
terms of
climate resilience and adaptation over
the long term
and biomaterials research in the
combined zone of okay if we
we create create productive ecosystems
what what
are the the um oil seed fruits
trees and so on that that we can use to
create the plastics of the future and so
on and so forth
um all of that is then also relevant to
the entire
mediterranean climate zone which
includes parts of australia south africa
california and so so i i feel it has
significance as a research
lab um even if it doesn't add
a big chunk off yeah i don't think we
should always think in hectares you know
or trees
a number of trees i think the most
important thing is we need to think
in ecological functionality and what a
foundation
restoring the ecological foundation and
what what a majorca or the balearic
islands like other
archipelagos can mean is that they can
inspire others and um uh
you know as common lands from a common
perspective yes we want to
we we don't want to grow as an office or
we don't want to have
lots of people we don't want to be a
super big bingo
a multinational ngo or whatever but what
we do is want
we want others to help to use these for
to to use the fortunes methodology
so so yes we you know our if you really
ask what is my dream then it would be
how can these four turns become the new
norm
instead of and remove that maximization
of return
investment per hectare norm how can we
make sure that this becomes the new norm
accepted by government so that everyone
will use it and it's open source you
know and you may use it you may name it
maybe
with a different name it's always good
to have a kind of a branded name because
that people will
recognize it easier but it works
and there are and yeah there are several
steps behind it
and and it starts in your case in
majorca it starts
with telling that story make sure that
that this or writing it down or publish
it or making it known
because it's very inspirational and then
you can peel it off
in working level steps in activities
and then you will see of course that
some steps are easy some steps are very
difficult will take years
and other steps you just go before you
know it so um
but we have now built those experiences
at covalent in four landscapes and we
are
working in eight landscapes now and that
is and we
are now already bringing on board other
landscapes as we are talking to you also
and others in other countries in
colombia
in brazil and so on
um and what we increasingly see is that
with this methodology we can help to
build always build that movement
we are partnering with other
international organizations to build
that movement
and um and yeah i think
the great thing of this time is that
that that
there will be carbon funding potential
becoming available it will be it will
become available
um and it can be it can be very much
helpful as a tool not as a driver
the driver should come from people and
from ecology
and from regenerative agriculture and
these kinds of things carbon can help
as an extra income if carbon is the only
driver then
my worry is that we will get tree
planting plantations
in the world where we should have other
type
and that that can be not be the same as
bringing ecology foundation back so um
so i'm very positive about what's going
on now
um uh in despite of co-fit and these
kind of things this this might be very
helpful
like in the case of majorca it can open
up a new opportunity
in in landscaping uh
and i'm also very positive about the
examples uh an island group like majorca
can play
for its for others uh like in the
mediterranean basin i mean
we all know that the mediterranean basin
was all
was forested before the romans started
to deforest
and and uh and there were a lot of water
catchment all year round
which is not the case anymore but
already in spain we see that if you do
the right things you get water cats from
the back
you're planting like planting trees
planting vegetation is planting rain
um yeah like that can you use the right
species on the right place
yeah the the um
potentially he is really
growing almost at a speed that is
difficult to
catch up with and there are more and
more people coming into this this
alliance that
um i i sent you this this proposal
balearis vet that much
my friend miguel ramos has started and
it starts with a million trees
and and some people like that hook
because everybody's not talking about
how good it is to
plant trees but it is much more com
complex proposal that that isn't just
saying like
any kind of trees it's it's basically
creating
um particularly paying attention to the
combined zone basically we're working on
how can we
turn degraded or even um
non-aerated land um
thailand into productive agroforestry
ecosystems and and build the soil and
but there's such a complexity of
other aspects of this transformation
because majorca is so heavily
tourism focused it's almost
yes there's all this exemplary
ecosystems restoration and how to apply
the four returns but
in the process of doing this here on
majorca
by by default one would also
create a model for the reinvention of
the role of tourism in the future which
of course now tourism is really
interested in um like i
only half a year ago before the corvette
crisis started
um i i started this conversation about
what would regenerative tourism look
like
turning the problem into a solution how
how could
large tourism businesses get involved in
investing
into the re-regionalization process that
that incentivizes farmers to
regenerate their land that that creates
capacity for
renewable energy production that looks
at um
bringing the transport infrastructure
closer to home in the sense of
moving towards towards public transport
driven by renewables
and and also looking strategically over
the long term
as the tourism industry into how to
diversify into
um a wider community-owned engagement
so when tourism contracts they actually
have helped
to build what comes in the future where
there still is tourism but much more
attractive
and a much more diverse interlinking
between how the
tourism becomes the the to some extent
the economic
engine of the transition yeah but that
that's
that is that's uh i think that you look
yeah i think that's the right way of
seeing it so you know i i'm the last one
who is against tourism as you may
know through my history but you have all
kinds of
sorts of problems of tourism and
as as in many things if this becomes a
monoculture
like in mallorca you are becoming
vulnerable that's what happens now
uh it's it's basically same thing with
monocultures in agriculture
or other monocultures in economic
development you know a wise company
will have a lot of different ways
you know a wise company will will have a
set of
different niches in which that company
is active
i see it i see it for instance in the
locomotive industry
so companies who have shares in bicycles
are doing well and if they have shares
in bicycles and cars you know the cars
are going down the bicycles are going up
so it's it's this is this is
so this is actually also a principle in
in ecology as you may
know and the fur the species who
disappear
who are becoming threatened are the very
the species who are in a very narrow
niche
and the the the general species who can
survive everywhere
like rats are you know they don't
they don't care um and i think if you
look at from that perspective you can
use
tourism as a motive for change and still
maintain a large part
in mallorca within the tourism sector
because it will not go away and you
don't want to have it go away because it
can also be part of the
spreading the word of what is it if you
can you imagine if you tell this
holistic story about this is our
development plan for the coming decades
for majorca
what does that mean for tourism well
also also because of the knock-on effect
that
so many of like the really big
spanish tourism enterprises that are
global
are all owned by mallorcan families
and they and they now have that center
of gravity
in the caribbean in the philippines and
asia in lots of beautiful places
also islands there you go many many
islands and
so whatever they would learn about the
four returns approach and long-term
transition over 20 years
here on majorca they could immediately
um
look into how they would then also
engage with the
the communities that they also have
assets or businesses
you know daniel it's um these things how
to continue with this
is is and that's i'm just out of the box
is is
we need in a way you need to bring
people together
in a good environment and share these
thinking
thinkings with presentations and then
come up with the next step and the next
step would be
i think a kind of a first document where
people
sign and say yes this is actually the
direction that where we want to go
and the next step could be the first
documents uh in in
on zoning and then with nice maps and
see you know this is a future
perspective the first drawing
of what the future could be and then
gradually
you need to create a kind of a yeah
group of people
uh who can do this in a professional way
and are the anchor
of change you know like alva laws the
anchor of change and we
be indeed as common and we support them
financially to make sure that they can
continue their work
because we know it's difficult this will
this change will not come you know like
this you need to have
people who draw this further and are on
top
on the potentials of of such an area
so so do you you do you actually hold
some
funds that are before the alvaro project
and as they
continue to do their work on the ground
they did you say we've done
this phase now and now we're doing this
yeah so yeah so so our experiences so
far is that
if we really say yes to a new area
so we have we have different uh maybe
you've seen different s
circles so we have a lower circle where
we really want to we as common land
would like to help driving this
for the for the coming decades and we
try to look for funding
and then we have the middle scale
landscape where that could be mallorca
maybe will help you with
all things we can do also to find
funding but we
cannot do too much and be too much
involved
and then we have an upper circle where
we set up platforms to exchange
experiences where all kind of type of
landscape can
tap into and and and use the tools that
we have developed together
and they can use the language so
brazilian ngo can
can tap into the platform say yes we
want to develop our fortrans landscapes
we use these tools and then we
get the fortune's name and whatever and
and and they can use that
also to raise funds because they have a
we create a common language together
that investors and vendors and carbon
emitters hopefully will understand at a
certain moment
and coming back to majorca if if
um yeah or sorry to to our experiences
so far he said it
if we really do it well it cost more or
less a half a million euros per year
to develop to keep a local team up and
running
to develop business businesses and
basically and make sure business
development happens
to continue with small grants activities
on the ground so that you can see
already some change happening
and learning farmers between each other
and then giving them seed money to stop
tilling for instance or doing less
stilling or whatever making shale swells
and that that whole set of activities
including
the funding of this group of people this
anchor
is this group of people doing the theory
you and so on will cost
half a million per year so we ourselves
now
have said okay if funders come to us we
just say listen
if you want to work with us this is how
we work if you want to partner with us
it costs you half a million euros per
year for 20 years 10 million euro for 20
years
and if you can assure or guarantee us
that funding
you know we really can take this up and
uh we can guarantee you that that we
that we
that this transformation will take place
but if they
say yeah we have 50 000 and
we we want a project we prefer to say
okay you can go to that organization but
we can't do it because we just don't
believe in it
you cannot transform things for 50 000
at the large landscape scale
you can do a project you can build a
school you can
support maybe a small regenerative
farmer
or company or or a local ngo to protect
this water catchment and plant some
trees
but that's not what we mean with
transformational change
that's just another project and we want
to enable that transformational change
so that
when funders come on board with 50 or
100 or whatever
that we have the right place and can say
yes 50 000
that's great and that's what we do now
in spain in spain we can say if fender
comes or an investment say
you have fifty thousand or a hundred
thousand you say that's interesting
let's talk to avalon because i think
within the big
pistol in the pieces we lack this piece
and that costs fifty thousand
so if you put it in here it will benefit
and if it's only a standalone project
then it will probably
will go on so so to for me to understand
this better
like as a how this could potentially
work here on majorca
this i completely agree it needs core
funding for the team to hold this over a
long period of time
and also it gives that team the
commitment that they can truly commit
their lives to making this process
happen
if they have a long-term um commitment
to to to their activity
and but this half a million would
basically land in common land
but then benefit to most
to the land yeah
so so how we work now with those four
core core landscapes
so we are funded as a team in common
land that's separate
and we have a separate budget line
um for alvalo or south africa or
australia
which is four hundred thousand euros
or five hundred thousand years it
depends with further thousand years and
that
is going directly to those local
landscapes you're not in between you
don't take anything out of it
no percentages or whatever because we
are offended
but you are holding because sometimes as
you build those local networks
there might not be i mean i can think of
a number of organizations
that that have the track record here
that they would give an investor the
confidence i can put money into that
account
but but you are offering the account as
well no like at this moment yes
but we are i mean all the law is open to
raise their own funds
but people make sure that they don't
need to worry about their
cornerstone their their existence and
they raise their own friends
so we we have raised funds with all the
law
to a care foundation for instance we
have we brought them on board
and they wanted to give the money to us
and we said no no you don't need to be
in between
you sign the contract directly with the
overall they're strong enough now
at the time that they were not strong
enough of course they they preferred
to e-care foundation prefer to do it
through us but as soon as the partner is
strong enough
you know why should we be there uh to to
to be
here but it's great to see that both as
possible and totally of course
is another huge potential here in
mallorca yeah
yeah so certainly yeah so
that would be another opportunity but
the tour care foundation will not funds
long-term processes but they will fund
projects
so so um it just depends you know
for instance balance the dutch of the
law you could say
they started in 2016
as a project cumberland project
netherlands because the dutch government
wanted to do something so we did the
scouting
we brought people on board and and
in 2019 they became independent
and and also with their independency as
a legal entity
all they found all the funding uh
we're going from our account uh let's
say the contracts
we're moving from contract between
common land and this and the funders
to towards contracts directly with
bangladesh but we still
fund weyland as cumberland because to
make sure that they can continue also
when it goes wrong when they have no
offenders
and that means we need to make sure we
get some extra funding from other
sources
to make sure we can do can keep up with
this this process
okay so so we need to probably have
another call
separate to this conversation to to
discuss how we do the next um steps and
and
in order to have a couple of minutes to
to talk about concrete next steps um
probably my colleague boss as well
because i
you know we have now a small group of
people who they call it the nurture
the the nursery where we nurture
potential new projects that we can work
on
and see how we can continue with them
and you're in that nursery
yeah we've already had a couple of
conversations with
um
great so thank you so much for this
conversation i want to ask a couple of
questions after the
we stopped the recording but this has
been wonderful and i i think that it'll
be really inspirational to a lot of
people
um to to been talked through this both
your journey um and how you how it
made you arrive at the four returns and
then it's quite remarkable to see the
the uptake and how it functions
everywhere
well in very different contexts or
already and it
and and it is putting
simple concepts that
ecologists or permaculturists would have
would feel familiar with but it's
putting it into a language
that um a government official
or an investor or a business person can
um
also understand and i think that's
hugely powerful
along with the the long-term commitment
that's uh
but unfortunately so many projects don't
understand that if you don't commit in
the long term you're wasting money
because
um it's simply yeah thank you very much
it is as i said it's it's lovely to to
speak with you
and yeah um i think maybe in
summarizing the lessons uh i've learned
so far
is that uh if you really work with this
kind of approaches or holistic
approaches the risks for investors
as well as for governments will go down
and everyone
everyone wants to see risks go down
but it's so difficult
to understand that this is actually
a risk return thing we are doing
um but returns are multiple and the
risks are also multiple
but you know working with two entities
that are
how to say dynamic like ecology and
people
um you know i think it's the most
difficult thing to do to work with these
two
dynamic uh items or or i don't know how
you call it or
entities and it's so challenging it's
and it's beautiful and it
yeah ultimately this is this will be
part of a new way of of thinking and
working
this beautifully ties our conversation
together because ultimately this working
with ecology and working with people
and if if we do it
right from a holistic perspective that
values science
but also holds that magic and that
connection to landscape
and place that we started off with um
then there's a healing of
us learning to see that we are part of
the ecology
and which is the the the big rift that
runs through our culture is that
too many people still think that there's
the environment out there and there's
human beings and culture and technology
here
and to understand that that it's it's
all
one complex dynamic process nested
from the local to the global is is
really where we need to
grow like that's the mature ration step
of our species right now to make that
yeah and and also to because it gives us
also a better understanding how we can
benefit from technology
while not because technology can play a
very important part in this but
it should not be the driver of processes
humans and ecology should be the driver
exactly that's often the one one thing
that i have
spent a lot of time thinking about
lately is is that we need to
on the one hand have a very
much deeper conversation about ethics
and
technology and what technologies to use
when and
which technologies to never use um
but at the same time we also need to
reposition
technology as part of nature as like
to understand that that if everything is
natural to some extent our cities then
also our technology
is part of this biophysical process and
and some technologies can be adaptive
and generate abundance and other
technologies are maladaptive
and will go extinct so in in that wider
sense
we just have to pay attention to what
technologies um
to use and and to revalue the
technologies
of the natural world that they do
complex regeneration work so much better
than any
um human made technology at this point
can do alone so it's it's bringing them
together yeah
wonderful yeah so we should go on but
we'll stop now and have so we have a
couple of minutes hold on